<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the funerall pompe, in which the body of Gustauus the Great, late King of Sweden, was carryed from the castle of Vbolgast, to the sea-side, to be transported into Swethland Together, vvith a strange apparition of the moone the night before.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02407</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12537</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103561</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839312</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839312</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3720</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02407)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3720)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1103:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the funerall pompe, in which the body of Gustauus the Great, late King of Sweden, was carryed from the castle of Vbolgast, to the sea-side, to be transported into Swethland Together, vvith a strange apparition of the moone the night before.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B[ernard] A[lsop] and T[homas], F[awcet] for Thom: Walkley, and are to be sold at his shop, neare White-Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Library of Congress.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gustaf --  II Adolf, --  King of Sweden, 1594-1632 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3720:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:3720:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->
            <p>A RELATION of the Funerall Pompe, in which the Body of GVSTAVVS the <hi>Great, Late King of</hi> Sweden, <hi>was carryed</hi> from the Caſtle of <hi>Vbolgaſt,</hi> to the Sea-ſide, to be tranſported into <hi>Swethland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TOGETHER, With a ſtrange apparition of the Moone the Night before.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>B.A.</hi> &amp; <hi>T, F.</hi> for <hi>Thom: Walkley,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, neare White-Hall. 1633.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="description_of_funeral_of_Gustavus_Adolphus">
            <pb facs="tcp:3720:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3720:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
            <head>THE FVNERALL Pompe of GVSTAVUS ADOLPHUS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fifteenth of <hi>Iuly</hi> laſt, being the day immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately foregoing that Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Pompe, in which the Hearſe of GVSTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VUS ADOLPHVS the late glorious King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> was remooved from <hi>Vbolgast</hi> to the Sea ſide, to bee ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported into his owne Kingdome, by the Queene his Widow, a prodigious apparition of the Moone happened. The Carryer or Poſt of <hi>Argentine,</hi> was travelling by Night with three more in his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3720:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
company, of whom one was a man of quality a Doctor of Phyſicke, and Mathematician; about nine of the clocke they were neere to a Village cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Eintritt.</hi> The Moone was then in her Wane, and grew horned (for it was foure dayes after the full) at which as they were looking, they perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcerned another little Moone, mooving up and down with various motions, about the upper horne of the true Moone. At laſt they joyned together; from which conjunction, a cleere and perfect circular figure was made, as if the Moone had then ſhined in her full. But long it continued not in that forme, but changed into the ſhape of a mans head<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> At which whileſt they gazed with wonder, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to know the face of the late King GVSTAVUS ADOLPHVS. In that forme, the Moone continued about a quarter of an houre before ſhee tooke her owne ſhape againe, that they might perfectly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver (not without feare and aſtoniſhment) the Kings head, with all the true lineaments of his face, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of his beard and hayre.</p>
            <p>From this portentuous apparition of the Moone, were divers opinions and diſcourſes rayſed among the people. Some remembred a propheticke ſpeech which the K of <hi>Swethla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi> whileſt living, was heard to make, that after he was dead, his Armies would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue victorious, and from thence a fame would be rayſed, that he himſelfe was living, and his death for a long time not bee generally believed, Others began to make a Religious praediction of it; and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3720:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
comparing the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church to the true Moone (becauſe the Church in all ages, like the Moones, has had increaſes &amp; decreaſes) and knowing that the <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh</hi> Empire has borne for theyr Armes the Moone, they compared that to the falſe Moone, which they had ſeene to move about the horne of the true Moone, and from that conjunction of them they propheſied, That God would in mercy cal the <hi>Turks</hi> and joyne them ſhortly to his owne true <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>The day following, being the ſixteenth of <hi>Iuly,</hi> the King of <hi>Swethlands</hi> Funerall, whoſe Hearſe had long remayned in the Caſtle of <hi>Vbolgast,</hi> was remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, to be tranſported into <hi>Swethland.</hi> The So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity was in manner following; In the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, Doctor IACOBVS FABRITIVS the King his Chapleyne, made a Funerall Sermon in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of the Caſtle of <hi>Vbolgast</hi> (where the Hearſe ſtood. His Text was taken out of the fift Chapter of the Lamentations of IEREMY; the words theſe; <hi>The Crowne of our head is falne off; Woe bee to vs now becauſe we have ſinned.</hi> Sermon being ended, the Funerall Pompe began to moove forward about five a clocke to the Sea-ſide, where the <hi>Swediſh</hi> fleet lay to receive his body. Colonell AXELIVS LILE marched foremoſt, followed by foureſcore and twelve rankes of Musketiers eight in a ranke, in mourning habit, and covered with hoods; after them in like habit, ſixe and thirty rankes of Divines two in a ranke, ſinging a mournfull Ditty as they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3720:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
paſt along. After whom, came fifty Students of the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> and an hundred and foureteene more, partly <hi>Germans,</hi> and partly <hi>Swedes,</hi> in long mourning Cloakes. Two great brazen Drummes were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed in the next place, after which, came ſixe Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peters, their Trumpets covered with blacke cloth, and each of them bearing a blacke Damaske Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, in which the Armes of <hi>Swethland</hi> were richly wrought with gold. After whom againe, came two brazen Drummes like the former, by men in the like habit; and ſixe Trumpeters in the ſame faſhion following.</p>
            <p>Immediatly after, came two Heralds cloathed in blacke ſilken robes, on which before and behind were the Armes of <hi>Swethland</hi> with great coſt, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity wrought in Needleworke of Gold, theſe two Heralds carryed either of them a Royall Scepter of exceeding great value. Then followed the Marſhall <hi>Ericas Guldenſlernius,</hi> with a wonderfull great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the chiefe Counſellors and Officers belonging to the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and the <hi>Megapolitan</hi> Dukes. Next followed, the Maſter of the Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance <hi>Leonard Torſtonſon</hi> carying a red Damaske ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, with him were three and thirty Barons, and Noblemen, euery one carrying a banner of ſeuerall colours, in which the Armes of thoſe ſeuerall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, which had beene joyned by conqueſt to the Crowne of <hi>Sweden,</hi> were moſt richly wrought in needleworke of gold. After euery one of theſe Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, a Horſe was led couered with blacke cloath, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3720:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
which, the ſame worke and armes were diſplayed in thoſe Banners which the Lords carried.</p>
            <p>Then followed <hi>Benedict Oxenſterne</hi> Maſter of the Horſe to the King of <hi>Swethland</hi> bearing a blacke Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of exceeding largeneſſe, and ſo heauy that three other were faine to helpe him in the carriage of it; upon this banner were curiouſly and richly wrought in gold, not onely the Armes of the Crowne of <hi>Swethland,</hi> but of all thoſe other ſeuerall Provinces which had bin diſplayed in the thirty three Banners going before, and heere ioyned into one. After this great Banner, came a ſtately Horſe, which King <hi>Guſtavus</hi> had us'd to ride on, his maine was excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding large and long. A rich couering of blacke, hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with gold hee had vpon him, and was adorned with feathers, blacke, white, and yellow. Vpon his backe in a wrought golden ſaddle, ſate <hi>Charles Horne</hi> Lord Chamberlaine of <hi>Swethland,</hi> clad in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of the dead King, and wearing a chaine of gold of exceeding great value. In his hand, hee carryed that ſword drawne, which King <hi>Guſtavus</hi> moſt uſed to weare, and at his ſaddle hung the Kings piſtoll yet ſtained with blood, as it came out of the battell of <hi>Lutzen.</hi> After him, came another Horſe couered with blacke, on which, a white Croſſe was wouen. Then went two Heralds cloathed in like manner as the former were, carrying two ſiluer Scepters, with others that carryed money, which they threw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people, all the way as the pompe paſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:3720:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->After this followed the Herſe it ſelfe; before which <hi>Crailſhem</hi> the Maſter of the Houſhold mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched alone. The Hearſe was ſmooth at the top, and round about it hung thoſe Armes of the ſeverall Provinces, which had beene before diſplayed in thoſe three and thirty Banners which the Barons carryed; and immediately after it, the great Armes of the Kingdome of <hi>Swethland,</hi> with the Crowne Royall, and Imperiall Globe; about which, was the Title written in great Letters, GVSTAVVS ADOLPHVS MAGNVS; with the houres of his Nativity and Death, ſpecified alſo. The Hearſe it ſelfe, was carryed by twenty Noblemen cloſe Mourners, under a large blacke Canopy, whoſe foure Corners were borne up by foure Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonels. After whom came forty other Noblemen, appoynted by turnes to carry the Herſe twenty at a time, and ſo to relieve each other all the way as the Funerall ſhould paſſe. Behind theſe, came the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Guard <hi>Stenboccius,</hi> with fifty of his Guard, theyr Speares covered over with blacke cloath, and themſelves attyred in long Cloakes. Then came two Marſhals, and after them the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> himſelfe, the two Megapolitan Dukes, with other great Princes, beſides the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors of the Prince Palatine and his Lady. Then followed ſome great Officers and Counſellers of the Kingdome of <hi>Swethland;</hi> of whom <hi>Herman Wrangell, Iohn Banner,</hi> and <hi>Steno Beilke,</hi> were the chiefe. After them came two other Heralds, <hi>Adam
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3720:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->
dam Pentius,</hi> and <hi>Caſſimire, Guildenſterne;</hi> then followed the Queene of <hi>Swethland</hi> the mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Widow of King GVSTAVVS, ſitting in a blacke Chariot drawne with ſixe Horſes, <hi>Gabriell Oxenſterne</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Guſtavus,</hi> and <hi>Matthias Soape</hi> waited on the Queenes Chariot; after her, came the Elector of <hi>Brandenburghs</hi> Lady, the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> the wiues of the two Megapolitan Dukes, the two Daughters of Duke <hi>Iohn Albert,</hi> the Daughter of the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Croy,</hi> and five Princely Ladyes of <hi>Anhalt;</hi> euery one of theſe great Ladyes was led by two Noble men, one at ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand; after theſe againe, followed two other Marſhals, and then in one faire company came all the Ladyes and Gentlewomen that waited vpon the Queene, and that belonged to the Marchioneſſe of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> and all thoſe other Princeſſes that before were mentioned; behinde them came all the Agents, Ambaſſadors, or Secretaries of the Cities thereabouts; and laſt of all, followed a troupe of the deceaſed Kings ordinarie Houſhold-ſeruants, who brought vp the reare of this long and great ſolemnitie.</p>
            <p>This Funerall Pompe, though it were great, had beene farre more magnificent and ſolemne, if the <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh</hi> fleete, which arriued the day after being <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> had come at the appoynted time; in which there were, an hundred Noble men with a great number of Souldiers all well provided of mourning attire, and bringing along with them many royall Enſignes,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3720:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->
Flagges, and Armours, which ſhould have beene ſhowne to advance the ſtate of the Funerall.</p>
            <p>When they were come from <hi>Vbolgaſt</hi> to the ſea-ſide, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence a bridge was made ouer to the ſhipping, they ſet the Hearſe downe vpon the ſhore; and <hi>Steno Beilkius</hi> ſtanding before the Queene, in her Name, and in the names of all the States of <hi>Swethland</hi> in a learned Oration, gaue thankes to the Electors, and the reſt of the Princes there for the loue they had ſhowed to his deceaſed Maſter. The Oration beeing ended, and ſome ſalutations paſſed the Kings Hearſe, was borne into the ſhippe to be tranſported with the Queene into <hi>Swethland;</hi> which was no ſooner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued, then a thundring peale of Ordnance from the Caſtle and Towne was giuen, and on the ſhore two bodies of Musketiers with a long and great Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley bad adiew to the body of that Martiall King.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3720:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->
            <head>An <hi>Elegie</hi> vpon the Death of the King of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Was late (great <hi>Heroë</hi>)</l>
            <l>e're wee could beleeue</l>
            <l>Thy death; and therefore</l>
            <l>late e're we could grieve.</l>
            <l>The Fates were pleas'd to reſpite <hi>Brittaines</hi> teare:</l>
            <l>So long a time, till ſhe had gather'd feares</l>
            <l>Enow to vſher ſuch a griefe: till doubt</l>
            <l>And long diſputes had vexed our Soules about</l>
            <l>The certaine truth, becauſe the ſilent skies;</l>
            <l>The Aire; or Earth in threatning prodigies</l>
            <l>Forgot to ſpeake ſo great a Worthies fall;</l>
            <l>And nature ſeem'd not ſenſible at all</l>
            <l>Of her deepe wound: vncertaine rumors here,</l>
            <l>In ſtead of Comets, brought preparing feare</l>
            <l>To play his part, e're ſorrow came; nor durſt</l>
            <l>Fame bring thy Story certaine at the firſt.</l>
            <l>Intelligence was growne ſo ſlow: that wee,</l>
            <l>Not as intelligence, but Hiſtorie,</l>
            <l>Are taught at laſt the <hi>Glorious Sweden's</hi> gone;</l>
            <l>Iuſt as we know that <hi>Philips</hi> mighty Sonne,</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:3720:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->That <hi>Cyrus, Caeſar</hi> and the reſt are dead.</l>
            <l>And now too ſtale the Sorrow ſeemes, to ſhed</l>
            <l>A teare; our eyes, even as we write, are dry.</l>
            <l>It is thy Storie, not thy <hi>Elegie</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That now is ſought for, and the wiſh of all</l>
            <l>To heare thy Triumphs, not thy Funerall.</l>
            <l>But oh, what pen! what eloquence ſhould tell</l>
            <l>Thy deeds, that never found a Paralell?</l>
            <l>What towring Muſe ſhould reach ſo high a flight</l>
            <l>As thy <hi>Heroicke Story</hi> muſt invite</l>
            <l>A muſe to take? Where ſhould we find a Straine</l>
            <l>Though from <hi>Elyſium</hi> wee ſhould call againe</l>
            <l>That <hi>Bard,</hi> that honour'd <hi>Thetis warlike Boy,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Or him that famed the pious Prince of <hi>Troy,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Or that lamented youth, whoſe ſtately ſtraines</l>
            <l>Enobled once <hi>Pharſaliaes</hi> tragicke plaines?</l>
            <l>And therefore be content in this as well</l>
            <l>To bee great <hi>Alexanders</hi> Paralell</l>
            <l>(As in thy Actions, and earely fall</l>
            <l>Thou wert) to finde no Poets pen at all.</l>
            <l>So much the greatneſſe of his deeds did fright</l>
            <l>The Poets of his time, no Muſe could write.</l>
            <l>Yet were thy acts more full of honour farre;</l>
            <l>More Iuſt nor leſſe ſucceſſefull was thy warre.</l>
            <l>What Muſe, alas, dares ſing thy firſt renowne?</l>
            <l>Before thou left'ſt thy North, to trample downe</l>
            <l>That high-ſwolne <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Empire (as erſt hee</l>
            <l>His <hi>Greece,</hi> to cruſh the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarchie)</l>
            <l>More weighty tasks remayn'd for thee at home</l>
            <l>Than him; and ſtronger foes to overcome,</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:3720:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->Before thy proweſſe could ſecure thine owne</l>
            <l>And lay thy future fames foundation.</l>
            <l>In ſtead of <hi>Athens,</hi> of the <hi>Theban</hi> ſtate,</l>
            <l>And other <hi>Grecian</hi> Provinces, whoſe fate</l>
            <l>Did exerciſe the youth of <hi>Philips</hi> Sonne:</l>
            <l>(Though there his Father had for him begun)</l>
            <l>The foes, that gave thee thy firſt triumphs, were</l>
            <l>The warlike <hi>Dane,</hi> and potent <hi>Polander.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The great <hi>Moſcovian,</hi> Monarch of ſo vaſt</l>
            <l>A territory, by thy ſword was chas'd,</l>
            <l>And forc'd, by yeelding vp a ſpacious land,</l>
            <l>To purchaſe peace at thy victorious hand.</l>
            <l>What would have crown'd another <hi>Heroës</hi> name</l>
            <l>Was but the entrance to <hi>Guſtavus</hi> Fame.</l>
            <l>And now the Fates eſteem'd thee fit to bee</l>
            <l>The vindicator of great <hi>Germany;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Th' Imperiall bird that ſoar'd in proudeſt ſtate,</l>
            <l>Gorg'd with ſo many Princes fals of late,</l>
            <l>Now all vnplum'd, and torne, is forc'd to feele</l>
            <l>The vengefull dint of thy victorious ſteele.</l>
            <l>Not ſuch true fame could <hi>Alexander</hi> boaſt</l>
            <l>When he ſubdu'd the gawdy <hi>Perſian</hi> hoaſt</l>
            <l>Within thoſe famous Strayts, or after neere</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Arbella</hi> fam'd for that great ſlaughter there;</l>
            <l>As thou of <hi>Lypſicks</hi> honoured field maiſt doe,</l>
            <l>And <hi>Tilly's</hi> fall. To paſſe with conqueſt through</l>
            <l>The well-arm'd <hi>German</hi> Empire, then o'rerunne</l>
            <l>Th' effeminate <hi>Perſians,</hi> greater glory wonne.</l>
            <l>But weigh the cauſes, and proceedings well,</l>
            <l>And then no more is hee thy paralell;</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3720:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->Whom wild Ambition onely did leade on</l>
            <l>To rob of freedome, euery Nation;</l>
            <l>Thou foughtſt to ſet oppreſſed Princes free,</l>
            <l>And to reſtore the <hi>German</hi> libertie:</l>
            <l>Him euery Kingdome, er'e he did appeare</l>
            <l>Like ſome great Plague, like mankinds Foe did feare:</l>
            <l>The many wronged Countries wiſh'd to ſee,</l>
            <l>And by thy iuſt drawne Sword reveng'd to bee.</l>
            <l>Wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch conquer'd to preſerve the conquer'd Foe</l>
            <l>And not to ruine, nor inthrall: And now</l>
            <l>Great <hi>Alexander</hi> yeelds to thee in glorie</l>
            <l>And till ſome ſecond <hi>Mars</hi> ariſe; whoſe Storie</l>
            <l>May prove hereafter ſuch as thine is now;</l>
            <l>Vpon the top of Honours houſe doe thou</l>
            <l>VVithout a Rivall, great <hi>GVSTAVVS,</hi> dwell;</l>
            <l>Enioy thy Fame without a Paralell.</l>
            <trailer>The End</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3720:8"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
